Guide to the Vine Deloria Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Vine Deloria papers
1969-2005
WA MSS S-2661
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
160.25
(170 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
The Vine Deloria papers consist of writings, correspondence, subject files, legal files, teaching files, organizational records, awards and tributes, photographs, audiovisual materials, and electronic media documenting the life and work of Vine Deloria. Writings, correspondence, and subject files form the bulk of the collection and document his involvement in issues relating to Native Americans. Organizational correspondence and organizational records document the many groups with which Deloria was affiliated.
Deloria, Vine
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from the estate of Vine Deloria on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 172 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 173 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Vine Deloria (1993-2005)
Vine Deloria Jr., author, theologian, historian, lawyer, and community organizer was a member of the Standing Rock Sioux. Born on March 26, 1933 in Martin, South Dakota near the Pine Ridge Oglala Sioux Reservation, he was the grandson of Tipi Sapa (Black Lodge), also known as Rev. Philip Joseph Deloria, an Episcopal priest and a leader of the Yankton band of the Nakota Nation. Deloria's father, Vine Sr. (1901–1990), studied English and Christian theology and became an Episcopal archdeacon and missionary on the Standing Rock Indian Reservation, to which he transferred the family's tribal citizenship. Deloria Jr.'s aunt was the anthropologist Ella Deloria (1881–1971).
First educated at reservation schools, Deloria graduated from Kent School in 1951. After serving in the Marines from 1954 through 1956, he graduated from Iowa State University in 1958 with a degree in general science. In 1963 he earned a masters degree in theology from the Lutheran School of Theology in Rock Island, Illinois.
Rather than joining the ministry, Deloria became executive director of the National Congress of American Indians, the largest intertribal organization in the United States. From 1964 through 1967 he lobbied Capitol Hill, worked to build tribal coalitions, and fought religious and political repression on the reservations. Under his leadership, membership in the NCAI grew from 19 to 156 tribes.
In 1969, Deloria published Custer Died for Your Sins: An Indian Manifesto, the first of more than twenty books and 200 articles he would write or edit on matters concerning Native Americans. A year later he received a law degree from the University of Colorado, and began his academic career at Western Washington State College at Bellingham, Washington.
While teaching at Western Washington State College he advocated for the treaty fishing rights of local Native American tribes and worked on the legal case that led to the historic Boldt Decision of the United States District Court for the Western District of Washington. In 1977, he became a board member of the National Museum of the American Indian.
Deloria became Professor of Political Science at the University of Arizona in 1978. Over the next twelve years he established the first master's program in American Indian Studies in the United States. From 1990 to 2000, Deloria taught American studies, law, history, religion and political science at the University of Colorado, Boulder. In 2000 he returned to Arizona and taught at the School of Law.
Vine Deloria Jr., died on November 13, 2005 in Golden, Colorado.
Scope and Contents
The Vine Deloria papers consist of writings, correspondence, subject files, legal files, teaching files, organizational records, awards and tributes, photographs, audiovisual materials, and electronic media documenting the life and work of Vine Deloria. Writings, correspondence, and subject files form the bulk of the collection and document his involvement in issues relating to Native Americans. Organizational correspondence and organizational records document the many groups with which Deloria was affiliated.
Arrangement
Organized into nine series: I. Writings, circa 1969-2005. II. Correspondence, 1969-2005. III. Subject Files, circa 1969-2003. IV. Legal Files, circa 1992-2004. V. Teaching Files. VI. Organizational Records, 1973-1995. VII. Awards and Tributes, 1970-2005. VIII. Photographs. IX. Audiovisual Materials, circa 1994-1996.
Civil rights workers -- United States -- Archives; Indians of North America -- Civil rights; Indians of North America -- Government relations; Indians of North America -- Legal status, laws, etc.; Indians of North America -- Politics and government; Audiovisual materials; Videocassettes; Born digital; Civil rights workers -- United States -- 20th Century; Deloria, Vine; National Congress of American Indians; National Museum of the American Indian (U.S.)
- Writings, circa 1969-2005; Series I; 12.79; (14 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Writings are in the order in which they were recieved. Boxes are listed in rough alphabetic order based on the box labels.
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes typescripts for many of Vine Deloria's books, some of which are accompanied by research materials; drafts for assorted writings projects, including works in progress at the time of his death; and television and movie projects.
  - American Indians, American Justice, circa 1983; 4 (Box 1)
  - The Nations Within, circa 1984; 4 (Box 1)
  - American Indian Policy in the Twentieth Century, circa 1985; 2 (Box 1)
  - Typescripts, 3 (Box 1)
  - Frank Waters Book - Articles, circa 1993 (Box 1)
  - Frank Waters, circa 1993; 2 (Box 1)
  - Frank Waters Anthology (Box 1)
  - Custer Died for Your Sins, circa 1969; 3 (Box 2)
  - We Talk, You Listen, circa 1970; 2 (Box 2)
  - God is Red, circa 1973; 3 (Box 2)
  - Indians of the Pacific Northwest, circa 1977; 2 (Box 2)
  - Indians of the Pacific Northwest - Doubleday - Research and Working Papers, circa 1977 (Box 2)
  - Behind the Trail of Broken Treaties, circa 1974; 3 (Box 2)
  - Research Materials - Behind the Trail of Broken Treaties - Dell, circa 1974 (Box 2)
  - Behind the Trail of Broken Treaties - Revised Edition, circa 1974 (Box 2)
  - The Metaphysics of Modern Existence, circa 1979; 4 (Box 2)
  - Indians of the Pacific Northwest - Photos and maps, circa 1977 (Box 3 Oversize)
  - Writing files, large projects (includes writings, correspondence, and research files (Box 4)
  - Writing projects II, 1989-, circa 1989 (Box 5)
  - Drafts of manuscripts (Box 6)
  - Fall 2005 Miscellaneous Manuscripts, etc. (Box 7)
    Includes a note describing the contents of boxes 7-10. These files were loose in Vine Deloria's library and office at the time of his death and may properly belong elsewhere among Deloria's files.
  - Fall 2005 Miscellaneous correspondence, etc. (Box 8)
    These files were loose in Vine Deloria's library and office at the time of his death and may properly belong elsewhere among Deloria's files.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Copies of electronic files are available through Access Services: Disk #1, #2 and #3.
  - Fall 2005 Manuscripts, Jung, etc. (Box 9)
  - Fall 2005 Manuscripts, Jung, etc. (Box 10)
  - Special writing projects (Box 11)
    Files combine writings, correspondence, and subject files, and includes notes from Vine Deloria on several of the projects. Also includes: Wounded Knee scrapbook.
  - Television/movie projects (Box 12)
  - Typescripts: Tribes, Treaties & Constitutional Tribulations; World We Used to Live In; C. G. Jung & Sioux Traditions (Box 13)
  - Typescripts: Tribes, Treaties & Constitutional Tribulations; World We Used to Live In; C. G. Jung & Sioux Traditions (Box 14)
- Correspondence, 1969-2005; Series II; 44.38; (37 boxes)
  Correspondence is arranged into five subseries: chronological, organizational, individual, publisher, and academic. Within indivudal boxes correspondence is arranged as received, either chronologically or alphabetically.
  The series includes correspondence relating to Vine Deloria's involvement in organizations relating to Native Americans, teaching, research, publishing, and other topics. Within the organizational corresondence, names of the included groups are listed in notes for each box.
  - Chronological correspondence
    - Correspondence, pre-1969, 1969-1973 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1974-1978 (Box 16)
    - Correspondence, 1978-1982 (Box 17)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1987 (Box 18)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1991 (Box 19)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 20)
    - Correspondence, 1994-1997 (Box 21)
    - Correspondence, 1997-2000 (Box 22)
      Office cabinet 1, drawer 1
    - Correspondence, 2001-2005 (Box 23)
  - Organizational correspondence
    - Ackbar Foundation to Education Testing Service (Box 24)
      This box includes correspondence relating to the following organizations: Akbar Foundation, American Civil Liberties Union, American Friends Service Committee, American Indian Anti-Defamation Council, American Indian Development Association, Arrow, Inc., American Indian Science and Engineering Society, Aspen Institute, Buffalo Bill Center, Center for Constitutional Rights, Chinook Fund, Cinnamon Productions, Christic Institute, Colorado Bicentennial Commission, Custer Battfield Memorial Land Purchase Program, Daybreak Films, Donner Foundation, Disability Rights Education and Defense Fund, James Draper/Kelly Associates, EATWOT, Educational Challenges, and Educational Testing Service.
    - Field Foundation to Indian Law Resource Center (Box 25)
      This box includes correspondence relating to the following organizations: Field Foundation, Ford Foundation, Forum for Contemporary History, Foundation for the Preservation of American Indian Art and Culture, Freewheelin' Films, Friends of Pyramid Lake, Friends of Carl Jung, Richard Fulton, Inc., Guggenhein Fellowships, IFCO, Interreligious Foundation for Community Organization, Indian Council Fire, and Indian Law Resource Center.
    - Indian Rights Association to National Indian Youth Council (Box 26)
      This box includes correspondence relating to the following organizations: Indian Rights Association, Institute for World Order, Institute for International Education, Lilly Foundation, National Coalition of Treaty Tribes, National Congress of American Indians, National Council of Churches, National Endowment for the Humanities, and National Indian Youth Council.
    - National Minority Military Museum - Sun Valley Center for Arts & Humanities (Box 27)
      This box includes correspondence relating to the following organizations: National Minority Military Museum, National Science Foundation, Native American Rights Fund, Native American Theological Association, Neihardt Foundation, Rattlesnake Productions, Rural Ethnic Institute, Sachem Foundation, San Diego State American Indian Program Review, Save the Children, Senate Committee on Aging, Sinte Gleska College, Small Tribes Organization of Western Washington, Society for the Study of Native American Relgious Traditions, Southwest Intergroup Council, Standing Rock Sioux Tribe, and Sun Valley Center for Arts and Humanities.
    - Sun Valley Movie Conference - Alan Walker, Program Corp of America (Box 28)
      This box includes correspondence relating to the following organizations: Sun Valley Movie Conference; Tribal Sovereignty Project; Theology in Global Context; Theology in the Americas; and Alan Walker, Program Corp of America.
    - White House: Papers & Correspondence (Box 29)
    - Acquisitions Committee, Denver Public Library - Standing Rock Sioux Tribe (Box 30)
      This box includes correspondence relating to the following organizations: Acquisitions Committee, Denver Public Library; American Indian Law Alliance; American Indian Science and Engineering Society; Colorado Historical Society; Denver Public Library; Evangelical Lutheran Church of America; Fund of the Four Directions; Hampton University; Inter-Tribal Bison Cooperative; Lannan Foundation; Native American Fish and Wildlife Association; National Indian Law Professors; Native Lands Institute; Society for Ecological Restoration; Snake River Institute; and Standing Rock Sioux Tribe.
    - National Museum of the American Indian; Rapid City Museum (Box 31)
      Office legal-size file cabinet, drawer 2; includes hard hat.
    - Council of 100 - Tides Foundation (Box 32)
      Not in alphabetical order.
      Office cabinet 1, drawer 4.
      This box includes correspondence relating to the following organizations: Council of 100; Buffalo Field Campaign; National Wildlife Fedaration Tribal Lands Advisory Council; American Indian Research and Policy Institute; American Indian Ritual Object Foundation; University of Arizona LLM Program; Gene Autry Musuem; Center for Western Studies, Augustana College, Sioux Falls; Colorado Center for the Book; Foundation for Preservation of American Indian Art and Culture; Indian Law Resource Center; Inter-Tribal Bison Cooperative; Kent School; Robert and Joy Leland Charitable Trust; National Wildlife Federation NEPA Committee; National Institute of Justice W.E.B. DuBois Fellowship Program; Native Lands; Rural Ethnic Institute; School of American Research; Standing Rock Historical Society; TKA Associates International; and Tides Foundation.
    - Niehardt Foundation - John Hay Whitney Foundation Grant (Box 33)
      This box includes correspondence relating to the following organizations: Neihardt Foundation, Lutheran School of Theology, Educational Foudnation of America, Rosa Minoka Hill Fund, Institute of the North American West, IRI-HITF Foundation, NativeLands Institute, Howard Simons Foundation for American Indian Journalists, Smithsonian Institute, TKA Community Development Grant, Western Socian Science Association, Western Political Science Association, John Hay Whitney Foundation.
  - Individual correspondence
    Individual correspondence is arranged alphbetically within each box.
    - Adams, Hank - Bridger, Bobby (Box 34)
    - Bridger, Bobby - Crosswait, Helen (Box 35)
    - DeGrazia, Alfred - Hansen, Evan (Box 36)
    - Hardaker, Chris - Luebben, Thomas (Box 37)
    - Lurie, Nancy - Pierce, Dick (Box 38)
    - Pierite, Joseph A., Chief - Sutton, Imre (Box 39)
    - Svendsen, David - Wood, Nancy (Box 40)
    - Armstrong, Dean - Irwin, Lee (Box 41)
      Office cabinet 1, drawer 2
    - Jaffe, Mark - Wright, Will (Box 42)
      Office cabinet 1, drawer 3
    - Archambeau, Kenneth - Wilkins, David (Box 43)
  - Publisher correspondence
    - Chronological, 1969-1976 (Box 44)
    - Chronological, 1977-1989 (Box 45)
    - Chronological, 1992-1996 (Box 46)
    - Chronological, 1997-2003 (Box 47)
    - Alphabetical, Akwesasne Notes - Westwater Press (Box 48)
    - Publishers by name, not in order (Box 49)
  - Academic correspondence
    - University of Arizona: Brand, Miles - Pre-Law Advisory Committee (Box 50)
    - University of Colorado, 1990s (Box 51)
- Subject Files, circa 1969-2003; Series III; 98.25; (88 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
  Subject files are arranged into six subseries based on format: files, binders, scrapbooks, printed materials, clippings, and card files. Within each subseries the files are organized in rough alphabetic order.
  The series consists of research into many areas relating to Native Americans, in particular legal isssues including treaties and landmark litigation, as well as clippings and other materials related to Deloria's life and work. Most descriptions are transcribed from box labels, binders, scrapbooks, etc.
  - Files
    - Active project files, arranged by subject (Box 52)
    - Active research files on monsters (Box 53)
    - American history to Pre-Columbian expeditions (Box 54)
    - Archaeology, Anthropology, Kennewick Man (Box 55)
    - Bering Straigs - settlement of North America; Pre-Columbian History - Mound Builders; Environmental Materials - Pro & Con for Indians as environmentalists; Folklore as Fact; Rock Art & Inscriptions (Box 56)
    - Bibliographies, legal indexes (Box 57)
    - Case files: Lumbee, Ottawat/Potawatomi, Seneca-Cayuga, Western Shoshone (Box 58)
    - Conferences - law and theology, traditional knowledge (Box 59)
    - Congressional reports - serial sets, colonial laws, allotment, Doolittle JOM, Percap-1923, Delegation Act, etc. (Box 60)
    - Congressional reports - serial sets, Removal Act, termination, etc. (Box 61)
    - Copies of dissertations, monographs, reports (Box 62)
    - Decennial Digest, Indian legends, myths (Box 63)
    - Education research files (Box 64)
    - Evolution and additions (Box 65)
    - Files on various tribes and native peoples (Box 66)
    - Files - Personalities, Kulas, Pam Colorado, Stanley, etc.; Pranks and Controversies, Churchill, othe frauds (Box 67)
    - Files relating to land rights, occupation cases, various tribes (Box 68)
    - General Indian articles; Morphic Resonance; Pre-Columbian articles; Catastrophism (Box 69)
    - Hanta Yo Controversy, Jamake Highwater correspondence and files (Box 70)
      - Jamake Highwater files (Box 71)
    - Indians, Legal and political articles (Box 72)
    - Indian Reorganization Act - Hearings to Repeal, Articles interpreting and commenting on IRA, Appropriations Acts, Termination/Alcatraz, BIA buildings (Box 73)
    - Indian Reorganization Act - Self-Government Hearings, Indian Congresses (Box 74)
    - Indians - Soul & Visions, Miscellaneous historical articles (Box 75)
    - Law Reviews, general Indian topics, non-Indian topics (Box 76)
    - Law Reviews, international status, Indian claims, water rights (Box 77)
    - Legislation files (Box 78)
    - Leventhal materials for Miamis and Delawares, Sacred Sites (1995) (Box 79)
    - Miscellaneous articles (Box 80)
    - Miscellaneous cases (by name) (Box 81)
    - Miscellaneous files on treaties, education, etc. (Box 82)
    - Miscellaneous files (Box 83)
    - Miscellaneous files (Box 84)
    - NAGPRA materials, Commissioner of Indian Affairs - Annual reports, Jesuit relations, land issues (Box 85)
    - Old treaty project files, Spanish-Mexican - Old drafts of chapters (Box 86)
    - Origins of the Solar System - Asteroid, Meteor, Moon, etc.; Geology - eras, strata; Scientific Measuring Devices (Box 87)
    - Peyote Case - Other Litigation (Box 88)
    - Pre-History - Zuni Creation Myths; miscellaneous chronological files, binders (Box 89)
    - Religious Freedom - Reports, Correspondence, Testimony (Box 90)
    - Religious Freedom - research files (Box 91)
    - Research files on religion (Box 92)
    - Research files on religion (Box 93)
    - Sacred Sites project (Box 94)
    - Sacred Sites project (Box 95)
    - Sacred Sites project (Box 96)
    - Sioux Indians - Anthropological, Historical, Cultural, Religious articles (Box 97)
    - Sioux Indians - Congressional reports (Box 98)
    - Sioux Nation - Federal documets, briefs (Box 99)
    - Treaties reference material (Box 100)
    - Treaty Rights: Congressional debates, historical articles, miscellaneous articles (Box 101)
    - Treaty study, law reviews (Box 102)
    - Tribal legal problems (Box 103)
    - Weird and Miscellaneous (Blue People, Roswell, aliens, etc.) (Box 104)
    - Working files, dinosaur binder (Box 105)
    - Yankton Sioux Litigation, Supreme Court decision and papers, Jurisdictional case - 1988 (Box 106)
  - Binders
    Binders are organized alphabetically by title.
    - American Indian Treaties course (Box 107)
    - Articles on Creation (Box 107)
    - Articles on Indians, 1970s (Box 107)
    - ASPR XI through Revisions (Box 108)
    - Case law involving 1868 treaties - non-Sioux (Box 108)
    - Cases on "Of Utmost Good Faith" (Box 108)
    - Cases on "Sacred as fee Simple" (Box 109)
    - Claims Cases (Box 109)
    - Creation - Evolution Litigation (Box 109)
    - Decennial Digest, Constitution, Religious Liberty & Freedom of Conscience (Box 109)
    - Decennnial Digest, Indian Treaties (Box 109)
    - Depredations Cases & Other Claims - Sisseton, Yankton, Lower Brule, etc. (Box 110)
    - Docket C-531, Black Hills Claim (Box 110)
    - Docket Nos 74 and 332-C, Black Hills Claim (Box 110)
    - Education & Schools, 1848-1965 (Box 110)
    - Executive Summary, Miami Tribe of Oklahoma Illinois Land Claim (Box 111)
    - Federal District Court Indian Cases (Box 111)
    - Federal Indian Legislation, 66th Congress to 100th Congress (Box 111)
    - Federal Religious Status Relevant to Indians Including NAGPRA (Box 111)
    - Federal Statues, At Large American Indians, Volumes 1-20 (Box 112)
    - Federal Statues Dealing with Sioux Indians (Box 112)
    - Guide to Records in the Military Archives Division Pertaining to Indian-White Relations (Box 112)
    - Indian Legislation Beginning in 1934 by Congress (Box 112)
    - Important Federal Statutes (Box 113)
    - Indian Bibliographies (Box 113)
    - Indian Cases Dealing With Application of the Fifth Amendment to Indians (Box 113)
    - Johnson-O'Malley, 48 Stat 596, Essay on Background, History and Application (Box 113)
    - Journals of the Contiental Congress (Box 113)
    - Legal Universe, 10th Amendment Cases (Box 114)
    - Legal Universe, Blacks (Box 114)
    - Legal Universe, Japanese, Chinese (Box 114)
    - Legal Universe, Labor, Criminals, Color of Law (Box 114)
    - Legal Universe, Natural World, Corporations, Property (Box 114)
    - Legal Universe, Territories, American Indians (Box 115)
    - Legal Universe Women, Children (Box 115)
    - Lower Federal Court Cases, Indian Treaties (Box 115)
    - Michigan Wisconsin Fishing Rights Cases (Box 115)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 116)
    - Miscellaneous Federal Cases (Box 116)
    - Miscellaneous Statues (Box 116)
    - Newspaper Clippings, Indian Matters (Box 116)
    - Newspaper Clippings on Indians (Box 116)
    - Newspaper items, non-Indians (Box 117)
    - Religious Freedom, Lower Court Cases, Indians (Box 117)
    - Sioux Indians, Lower Federal Cases (Box 117)
    - State Court Cases (Box 117)
    - Statutes dealing with Commissions to the Indians (Box 118)
    - Supreme Court Cases, Indians to 1870 (Box 118)
    - Supreme Court Cases, Indians, 1871-1910 (Box 118)
    - Supreme Court Cases, Indians, 1911-1960 (Box 118)
    - Supreme Court Cases, Indians, 1961-1980 (Box 118)
    - Supreme Court Cases, 1981- (Box 119)
    - Supreme Court Cases, Mexican Americans (Box 119)
    - Supreme Court Cases, Non-Indian (Box 119)
    - Supreme Court Cases, Religious Freedom (Box 119)
    - Treaties, Decennial Digest, Supreme Court Digest (Box 120)
    - Treaty Book, Great Britain, Canada (Box 120)
    - Treaty Cases, Lower Courts, Non-Indian (Box 120)
    - Tribes & States, William James Sidis (Box 120)
    - Tucson Artifacts (Box 120)
    - Tuscon Artifacts (Box 121)
    - Wisdom of Congress Cases (Box 121)
    - Volume IIB: Ratified Agreements, Conventions, Railroad Agreements, Settlement Acts (Box 121)
    - Untitled binder of legal cases (Box 121)
    - Untitled binder of legal cases (Box 122)
    - Untitled binder of legal cases (Box 122)
    - Untitled binder of treaties (Box 122)
    - Untitled binder of treaties (Box 122)
    - Untitled binder of treaties (Box 122)
    - Untitled binder of appropriation acts (Box 122)
  - Scrapbooks
    Scrapbooks are organized alphabetically by title.
    - American Indians, American Justice (Box 123 Oversize)
    - Custer Died for Your Sins, reviews (Box 123 Oversize)
    - The Metaphysics of Modern Existence; The Aggressions of Civilization; A Sender of Words; American Indian Policy in the 20th Century (Box 124 Oversize)